Register to The Zo Elliott Papers
Yale University Music Library
The Zo Elliott Papers
1861-1977
MSS 18
Yale University Music Library
10
(19 boxes)
Music, correspondence and other papers, photographs; and miscellaneous items by and about the American composer Zo Elliott (1891-1964)
Elliott, Zo, 1891-1964
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to researchers by appointment. There are no restricted materials in the collection. Please contact the Special Collections staff to schedule an appointment.
Some of the materials may be stored at the Library's off-campus shelving facility, so researchers should allow at least two business days to have the appropriate boxes paged.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Zo Elliott Papers were established in the Music Library of Yale University by Elliott's sister, Mildred W. Smith, in 1964.
Arrangement
In 10 series as follows: I. Correspondence. II. List of musical works, program notes, brochure. III. Photographs. IV. Clippings and press releases. V. Poetry and prose by Zo Elliott. VI. Miscellaneous items. VII. Statistical information and letter relating to John Brown. VIII. Piano roll. IX. Musical works by Zo Elliott. X. Musical works by other composers.
Scope and Contents
The Zo Elliott Papers contain sketches, manuscript scores, and published editions of Elliott's musical compositions, including operas, chamber works, piano pieces, songs, and choral music. Elliott's life and work are further documented by: correspondence; programs, clippings, and press releases; writings by and about Elliott; photographs; and miscellaneous items.
Biographical / Historical
Alonzo ("Zo") Elliott was born in 1891 in Manchester, New Hampshire. He was educated at St. Paul's School (Concord, New Hampshire), Phillips Academy (Andover, Massachusetts), Yale University, Cambridge University, and Columbia Law School. Elliott also studied voice with De Sadler of New York and Berlin, and piano with Harry Whittemore of Manchester, New Hampshire. His best known composition is "There's a Long, Long Trail," one of the most popular songs from the era of World War I. (Elliott wrote the music; the words are by Stoddard King.) That song was not the only example of Elliott's interest in military music; he composed an opera, Top Sergeant, and he wrote an article about the background of the Civil War song "John Brown" which showed that the John Brown of the song was a soldier in Boston, not the famous abolitionist of the same name. Zo Elliott died in Wallingford, Connecticut in June, 1964.
Composers -- Correspondence; Music -- United States -- 20th Century; Operas -- Scores; Piano music; Songs; Elliott, Zo, 1891-1964; King, Stoddard, 1889-1933
- Correspondence, Series I
  - Concerning the collection, I.A
    - Letters concerning the collection, 1964-1977; 35 items (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - To 'Zo Elliott, I.B
    - West, Charles, 1913 Nov 6 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      General
      1 typed letter signed, re publication of song.
    - West and Company, 1913 Dec 9 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Yearsley, Claude B., 1919 Oct 6 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      1 typed letter signed, re business proposal.
    - King, Stoddard, 1926 Jan 23 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      1 autograph letter signed, re lyrics for song.
    - Pearkes, L.V., 1927 Nov 17 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      1 typed letter signed, photocopy, re final payment.
    - McCann, J.L., 1932 Mar 10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      1 typed letter, re dues for the American Legion.
    - King, Stoddard, no year Mar 28 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      1 typed letter signed, thanks for check received.
- List of musical works, program notes, brochure, Series II
  - "Zo Elliott Music Library", 1964 Aug 10; Smith, Harold A., Mrs.; 2 leaves. 28 cm. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Typescript.
  - List of compositions, [1965]; [2] leaves. 28 cm. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Frederick Smyth Chorale Program, 1965 May 23; [4] p. 21 cm. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    3 copies, one with note signed by William R. McAllaster. First performance of Armistice.
  - Program notes for Top Sergeant, no date; 2 p. 28 cm. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brochure for 'Zo Elliott, lecturer on music, no date; [2] leaves. 12 cm. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Photographs, Series III
  - Miscellaneous photographs, 1861-1965; 11 items (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Clippings and press releases, Series IV
  - '"John Brown" of Famed Song Hub Soldier,' The Boston Herald, 1930 Sep 21; Manchester, H.F. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 'Sheds new light on the origin of "John Brown" song,' [The Boston Herald], [1930 Oct 5] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "John Brown's body never mouldered", [1937-1938] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Song for two John Browns," The MUSIC Magazine/Musical Courier, p. 8-10., 1962 Apr; Elliott, Zo, 1891-1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes a signed note dated 1962 Mar 9.
  - "Zo Elliott compositions highlight of concert," Manchester (N.H.) Union Leader, 1965 May 24; Fischer, Herbert R. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 'Who "Mademoiselle from Armentières" was.', 3 leaves. 26 cm. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Photocopy of typescript.
    Press release.
- Poetry and prose by Zo Elliott, Series V
  - "To: M.W.E.", 1918 Jul; [1] leaf. 28 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "History of Long Trail", no date; 4 leaves. 28 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Holograph in ink and pencil.
  - 'History of "There's a Long, Long Trail"', [4] leaves. 28 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - '"John Brown's Body" and other great military songs', no date; 26 p. 28 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Typescript, with corrections in pencil.
  - "John Brown's Body", no date; 10 p. 28 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - ["What Music has Meant to Me"], no date; 3 leaves. 28 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    2 copies.
  - Dedication for What Price Glory, no date; [2] leaves. 78 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Miscellaneous items, Series VI
  - Miscellaneous, 10 items (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Bookplate for Alonzo Elliott, picturing his home in Manchester, New Hampshire. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 4 envelopes. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Key and 2 key tags. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 2 poems in Russian. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Statistical information and letters relating to John Brown, Series VII
  - Hallgreen, Frances J., 1928 May 5; [3] p. 21 cm. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    autograph letter signed, Malden, Massachusetts, to Mr. Staniels, n.p.
  - Statistical information re John Brown's quartet, no date; [1] leaf. 28 cm. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    3 copies.
- Piano roll, Series VIII
  - There's a Long, Long Trail A'Winding. [Phonoroll], [1915]; Elliott, Alonzo, 1891-1964; 1 roll
    Duo-Art 103415.
    'Zo Elliott, piano.
    Edition recorded: M. Witmark and Sons, c1915.
    For player piano.
- Musical works by Zo Elliott, Series IX
  - Captain of the Crew., c1907 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    For piano.
  - Tulips., c1907 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    For voice and piano, words by Laura Elliott.
  - There's a Long, Long Trail., c1913-1916; 13 items (Box 2, Folder 2)
    For voice and piano, words by Stoddard King.
    1 copy includes Chinese translation.
    Parts for orchestral and band arrangements included.
  - Oh! Oh! Abdullah!, c1915; 4 items (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - The World Was Made For You And Me, c1917-1918 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    For voice and piano, words by Edward Lockton.
    Waltz version for piano included.
  - There's a Wee Little Cottage, c1918; 11 items (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Parts for orchestral arrangement included.
  - Burma Bells, c1920 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    For voice and piano, words by 'Zo Elliott.
  - In the Heart of Paradise, c1920; 5 items (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Oo: Oo: De Cologne!, 1923 Jan (Box 2, Folder 5)
    For voice and piano, words by John Milton Hagen.
  - Oh, Yes, Sir, 1923 Apr 12; 4 items (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Opening Number: The Beauty Shop, 1923 Apr 12 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Run Sheep Run, 1923 Apr 12 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    For voice and piano, words by Kate Horton and John Milton Hagen.
  - Troubador Song, 1923 Dec (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Music Written for a Mexican Garden. [from Jolanda?], 1923; 16 items (Box 2, Folder 7)
    For flute, violin, and violoncello.
    Parts for orchestra included.
  - Reflection, 1923; 4 items (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Serenade, 1924 Mar (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - T'amo de Lecco, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Trail O' My Heart, c1924; 27 items (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Bass and baritone parts included.
  - Enchanted River, c1925; 21 items (Box 2, Folder 10)
    1 copy includes Russian translation.
    Also included are a scores an arrangement for male chorus (TTBB) and piano, and parts for orchestral arrangement.
  - [Jolanda?], 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Opera, libretto by Edward Lowrey.
    Sketches.
  - Top Sergeant, 1925-?
    Opera in four acts, the libretto is by 'Zo Elliott based upon Maxwell Anderson's What Price Glory.
    - List of themes. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Workbooks. (Box 6–7)
    - Scores (Box 8)
      Piano-vocal, Acts II-IV.
      Final, corrected piano-vocal.
      Voice parts for Sergeant Quirt, The Three Marines, Lewisohn, Lt. Moore and Cognac Pete, Charmaine.
    - Scores (Box 9–10)
      Scores, complete, 2 copies of Act III.
      Orchestral corrections.
      Addenda.
    - Parts (Box 11)
    - Literary source (Box 11)
      What Price Glory, by Maxwell Anderson, and German translation (Rivalen)
    - Sketches (Box 12–19)
  - Pour Réveillon, 1930-1931; 4 items (Box 2, Folder 11)
    For voice and piano, words in French.
  - Caucasian Love Song, c1932 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    For voice and piano, words by Philip Seeley.
  - Annapolis: Midshipman's March, c1932-1933
    On a melody by Maurice La Farge.
    - For voice and piano, words by 'Zo Elliott and Elizabeth Demarest, 27 copies. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - For voice and piano, words by N.J. Francis and 'Zo Elliott, 3 copies. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Parts for band arrangement, 2 copies. (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Parts for orchestral arrangement. (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Arrangement for male chorus (TTBB) and piano., 20 items (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Sketches. (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Shall I Compare Thee: Elizabethan Sonnet, 1939-1956; 13 items (Box 3, Folder 5)
    For voice and piano, words by William Shakespeare.
  - Armistice, 1939 Oct; 16 items (Box 3, Folder 6)
    For male chorus (TTBB), piano or organ, and drums. Words by Stonewall Jackson and Rupert Brooke.
    Arrangement for baritone, chorus (SATB), and piano, by William R. McAllaster included.
  - British Eighth March: Chungking Hymn, c1943-1954; 25 items (Box 19, Folder 1)
    Arrangement for voice and piano, words by John Masefield is included.
    Also arrangements for band with score and parts, for chorus of mixed voices, unacc., and for male quartet (TTBB), unacc. are included.
  - Bluebird, c1961; 4 items (Box 3, Folder 7)
    For voice and piano, words by Alice Hunt Bartlett.
  - Ave Maria, no date (Box 3, Folder 7)
    For voice and piano, words by Lord Byron.
  - Aviation Glide, no date (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - El Chivato: Billy the Kid, no date; 24 items (Box 3, Folder 8-11, Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    Opera in four acts.
    Synopsis included in folder 8.
  - Comrade O' Mine, no date (Box 4, Folder 3)
    For voice and piano, words by Fred E. Bowles.
  - Hooray for Love, no date (Box 4, Folder 3)
    For voice and piano.
  - If a Girl, no date (Box 4, Folder 3)
    For piano
  - Jamie Mackee, no date (Box 4, Folder 3)
    For voice and piano, words by Blanche Elliott-De Moulpied.
  - Juvenile works, no date; 24 items (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Let Us Suppose, no date (Box 4, Folder 5)
    For voice and piano, words by Benné Dixon.
  - Love is Like the Sunshine, no date (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - May Time, no date (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Minuet, no date (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Parts for string quartet.
  - Miscellaneous works and notebooks, no date; 18 items (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
  - Phillipian March, no date; 2 items (Box 4, Folder 8)
    For voice and Diano, words by 'Zo Elliott.
  - Recruit's Song, no date (Box 4, Folder 8)
    For voice and piano, words by E.J. Webb and 'Zo Elliott.
  - Silver and Gray, no date; 7 items (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Parts arranged for band by Lt. Resta included.
  - So Good, So Bad, no date; 6 items (Box 4, Folder 10)
    For voice and piano, words by Massa Dixon, sketch.
  - Soldier, Soldier, no date (Box 4, Folder 10)
    For voice and piano, words by Rudyard Kipling.
  - Sweetheart of My Childhood, no date (Box 4, Folder 10)
    For voice and piano, without text.
  - Telech, no date (Box 4, Folder 10)
    A ballet, sketch.
  - Untitled work, no date; 3 items (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Zhdi Menia: 620 March: 620 and 612 March, no date; 9 items (Box 19, Folder 2)
    Title romanized: Wait for me.
    For voice and piano, words in Russian and English, by K. Simenov.
    Arrangement for band, score and parts included.
  - Waltz No. 2, no date; 3 items (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Workbooks and composition exercises, no date (Box 5, Folder 1-6)
- Musical works by other composers, Series X
  - Alexander's Ragtime Band, c1911; Berlin, Irving, 1888-1989 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    For voice and piano, words by Irving Berlin.
    Commentary attached to front cover, typescript.
  - Hinky Dinky Parlez-Vous, c1911; Rice, Gitz (Box 5, Folder 7)
    For voice and piano, words by "Red" Rowland.
  - I Wonder, c1925; Fenner, Beatrice (Box 4, Folder 7)
    For voice and piano, words by Beatrice Fenner.
    Incomplete.